For more than half a century,
anti-American propagandists have waged a
demoralization campaign against us.
Generations of Americans have been
force-fed lies designed to beat us into
a state of submission and self-loathing.
We've been taught to hate ourselves, to
hate the West, and to hate the figures,
mostly white, mostly male, who built
America. We're all familiar with their
narrative. America is uniquely evil
because of racism, slavery, colonialism,
imperialism, and so on. They've waged
intellectual warfare against our
founding fathers and national heroes.
They desecrated their reputations, tore
down their statues. Their rewriting of
history is such flagrant propaganda that
would make Pravda blush. That doesn't
mean that it's not pervasive or
successful. One professor from the
University of Wisconsin spent 11 years
administering historical literacy tests
to his students. He discovered that they
overwhelmingly believed that slavery
began in the US [music] was almost
exclusively an American phenomenon. A
view shared, by the way, with at least
one United States senator who attended
Harvard Law. The
>> United States didn't inherit slavery
from anybody. We created it.
>> Despite almost total ignorance on the
topic, one Washington Post poll found
that a 67% majority of the public says
the legacy of slavery affects American
society today.
>> That question every black person gets,
which is, "Slavery was a long time ago.
Why don't you get over it? How do you
get over something that is as
foundational to your society as anything
can be foundational?
>> We've been told that the history of
slavery is straightforward and
uncontroversial. We've been told that
black slaves were mostly captured by
whites, that white colonists in the
Americas routinely enslaved free black
men, and that more black people were
enslaved than whites. And we've been
told that we're not allowed to question
any of that. Well, enough is enough.
We're launching a monthly series setting
the record straight on various
historical topics. [music] We'll give
you the facts that the propagandists and
idiot school teachers have left out of
the mainstream curriculum. And we'll
start today by taking on one of the
central claims of modern anti-American
mythology. This is the real history of
slavery.
[music]
Historians and political pundits spend a
lot of time talking about the
transatlantic slave trade, the 350-year
period in which an estimated 12.5
million slaves were brought to the
Americas. But what we don't learn in
school is where those slaves actually
went. Just under half of them, an
estimated 5.4 million, went only to
Brazil and many more went to the
Caribbean. 1.2 million went to Jamaica.
More than 900,000 to St. Dominique and
889,000 to Cuba. The grand total of
slaves brought to the future United
States was about half the number brought
only to Cuba. 472,372
or 3% of the total. The ones who came to
the 13 colonies were the lucky ones. In
the context of global slavery, getting
put on a ship to New Orleans was really
a best case scenario. If you think
American slavery was bad, wait until you
see what happened to the ones who didn't
make it here, and we'll show you that
over the course of this video. But
first, we start with a West African
country you've likely never heard of,
the Kingdom of Deie. Deomi was not a
peripheral player in the Atlantic slave
trade. It was central to it. The
kingdom's wealth, its military power,
and its cultural splendor were built
entirely on the systematic capture,
sale, and export of human beings. By the
end of the kingdom, an estimated 1.9
million slaves came from West African
coastline controlled by the Dehomie. The
kingdom obtained its slaves by waging
perpetual warfare upon its neighbors. In
the 19th century, a Deomian king named
Gzo described the slave trade as the
ruling principle of my people. It is the
source of their glory and health. Their
songs celebrate their victories and the
mother lulls the child to sleep with
notes of triumph over an enemy reduced
to slavery. Now, in many cases, the
kingdom of Deomi obtained these slaves
by deploying an all female military unit
called the Deomi Amazon. They were the
chief slave catchers of the empire. The
Amazon would raid nearby towns and
return with large contingents of slaves
along with the heads of anyone who
resisted. One missionary who visited the
country in 1861 described some of Tomy's
soldiers as equipped with three- foot
long straight razors which they held
two-handed and which were supposedly
capable of splitting a man into two
halves. According to one historian,
quote, "When Amazon walked out of the
palace, they were preceded by a slave
girl carrying a bell. Sound told every
male to get out of their path, retire a
certain distance, and look the other
way. If the men didn't get out of the
way, they stood a very good chance of
being split in half. The homie Amazon
ran roughshod over the region. An
American missionary named Jacob Bower
discovered 18 depopulated towns over 60
m near the territory of Deomi. The death
toll was massive. Gzo, the king we
mentioned earlier, built a palace called
the Singbo Gi, which used human skulls
for bricks and human blood as mortar.
His throne sat on the skulls of four
enemy chiefs.
Assuming you survived a Domi raid, which
wasn't likely, and were taken captive,
it was far preferable to be sold to
Europeans than to remain in Domi. Slaves
they couldn't sell or that they didn't
want anymore were subjected to torture
and public executions. That's because
the Demomians believe that they could
communicate with the gods through human
sacrifice. On average, they dispatched
about 500 people a year. Roughly 10%
were killed at the annual custom, a
yearly mass slaughter. In 1893, the
Sacramento Daily Union reported, quote,
"Hundreds are annually put to death with
the most savage tortures. They are
dismembered limb by limb. They're tied
to posts and hounds are set to worry
them to death. They are securely
fastened to the ground near the nests of
the ferocious ants of the country that
attack them and tear their flesh bit by
bit away. The spectacle of a still
living man with his body halfeaten by
the ants being not infrequently seen.
Near the royal palace there are long
avenues. And when the king desires to
receive an embassy with unusual pomp,
jibbits are erected and on these are
hung head downward dozens of hapless
slaves there to remain guarded by the
king's soldiers until death puts an end
to their sufferings. Even before the
breath has left the body, however, the
vulture into a [music] sacred bird
begins his work and the screams of the
sufferers torn to pieces by the greedy
birds render the vicinity of the palace
hideous.
Such gruesome accounts were an ironic
outcome of European powers ending the
slave trade decades earlier. Unsellable
slaves were only useful as human
sacrifices. But the annual mass
execution festivals weren't even the
most brutal event in Dhomi. According to
the Sacramento Daily Union, they were
quote far surpassed by the scenes which
take place when the new monarch is
crowned. 500 to a thousand men are put
to death in order to provide the
deceased king with a suitable retinue in
the other world. Then blood flows in
streams on the accession of a present
ruler. So great was the number of those
wantingly slain that a large trench was
made in the ground in which a canoe was
placed. The blood of the murdered men
was conducted by conduits into the
trench until its quantity was sufficient
to float the boat. This was the level of
barbarism that defined the intraaffrican
slave trade. The Deomi literally sailed
canoes in the blood of their slaves.
They butchered thousands of slaves as an
offering to their king. Slavery and
barbarism were a fundamental part of
their culture. Now, it's worth noting
here that although black Africans
themselves did have slaves and routinely
sold slaves, they weren't big players in
the trans oceanic transportation of
slaves. They also didn't participate in
the raids on the coast of Europe that
we'll address later in this episode.
That's because quite frankly, they just
didn't have the technology to do that.
But that's never addressed by mainstream
historians, nor are the details on the
enslavers in Tomomi. Consider, for
example, Ken Burns's recent PBS
documentary on the American Revolution,
where he uses passive [music] voice to
creatively skirt the question of who
exactly did the enslaving. Tens of
thousands were from West Africa,
captured from what is now Sagal, Gambia,
and Gabon, Angola, Congo, and the Ivory
Coast, Nigeria, Cameroon, and Ghana.
>> It would be inconvenient for
propagandists like Burns to point out
that the slaves were already enslaved by
other Africans, mostly women, by the
way. That reality makes the white guilt
narrative a little less straightforward.
And if they did mention it, they'd also
be obliged to point out another
inconvenient fact that the horrors of
Tomi ended in 1894 because French
colonizers invaded the country and
burned the royal palaces. The French who
freed their slaves in 1848 built
hospitals, schools, instituted social
services mostly through Catholic
missionaries. In other words, they
brought civilization to some of the most
savage people in human history.
This year, our sponsor Pure Talk is
celebrating President's Day by giving
you great wireless service for only 25
bucks a month. Get unlimited talk, text,
and plenty of data for the cost of only
one or two meals out. No reason that
wireless service needs to be in the
hundreds. So, make the switch and feel
better about your finances. The low
price isn't the only perk, either. Uh,
you can feel good knowing your wireless
company is based right here in the US
with an American customer service team
and a passion for supporting veterans.
Pure Talk uses the same towers as the
big carriers. So enjoy superior 5G
coverage without the inflated price.
Just $25 a month for talk, text, and
plenty of data. No contract, no
cancellation fee. Go to
puretalk.com/walsh and you'll get 50%
off your first month. Again, it's
puralk.com/walsh to make the switch to
pure talk. What do Snow White,
Cinderella, and Smallox blankets have in
common? They're all fairy tales. For
decades, [music] you've been told that
you live on stolen land. that we are
right now on stolen land, that the
Indians were peaceful.
>> Native Americans, we massacred them.
>> Your ancestors [music] committed
genocide.
And guess what? None of it is true. The
Native Americans were some of the most
savage fighters ever known to man.
Raiding, scalping, torturing, even
eating enemies. It was better to lose a
battle to the US Army than to get wiped
out by a rival [music] tribe. And why
did the story completely change in the
1960s? It turns out there's a lot more
to the American Indians than Hollywood
directors and school teachers want you
to know. This month, we blow up the
biggest myths about the American [music]
Indians and reclaim the real history
that was stolen from us. This is the
real history of the American Indian.
[music]
Slavery's
roots go back at least to ancient times
in Babylonia, Egypt, Greece, and Rome,
as well as the American Indian empires
of Mexico and South America. One of the
earliest references to slavery comes
from this clay tablet from a Middle
Eastern city called Uric, dated back to
around 3,300 BC, which gives us a look
into Babylonian slavery, for example. On
one surface of the tablet, there's a
notation showing that at least 213
people were designated by the sign
combination salur, which means female
[music] and male slave, respectively.
Young slaves and specifically infants,
were considered the most valuable. Poor
parents often sold their own children
into slavery. The historian Amanda Poty
writes in her book, Weavers, Scribes,
and Kings, quote, "A woman named Kuet
made what must have been a heartbreaking
decision. she would sell her daughter.
We've encountered this phenomenon before
in the OR3 period when a family had to
sell a child into slavery because that
was the only way that the child would be
able to be fed and to live that the
parents could survive. The price of the
baby was 30 shekels. Thousand years
later, Orur Namu, the leader of the
Sumerian dynasty of in southern
Mesopotamia, issued a legal code with
different penalties depending on whether
you were legally classified as free or a
slave. A more famous ancient reference
to slavery comes from the Code of
Hammurabi, which established slaves as
property, set rules for interactions
between slaves and their owners,
included penalties for harboring
fugitive slaves, and had class-based
punishments for crimes based on whether
the perpetrator was free or slave.
Slavery was so common in ancient Greece
that most classical scholars agree that
Plato simply assumed that there would be
non-Greek slaves in the ideal city in
the Republic. In Aristotle's politics,
he openly declared, quote, "Some men are
by nature free and others slaves, and
that for these latter, slavery is both
expedient and right." Indeed, in ancient
Athens, slaves comprise more than 35% of
the population. Athenian slaves were
private property [music] and could be
bought and sold. Slaves who worked
domestic jobs or skilled crafts had a
decent shot at acquiring freedom. But
there were also slaves who were sent to
the mines. They were leg ironed,
routinely starved, savagely beaten,
seldom saw daylight, and were worked to
death with a typical life expectancy of
about 4 years. Athens, by the way, was
the best place to be a slave in the
ancient world. In Sparta, slaves known
as hellets outnumbered citizens 7 to1.
And one thing that made them unusual is
that they were public, not private
property. But because they vastly
outnumbered citizens, Sparta used brutal
secret police to intimidate the slaves
and gave the secret police power to
execute slaves who seemed strong or
rebellious. Sparta was a total apartheid
state and banned hellets from using the
same roads as Spartan citizens. Every
year, Sparta's leaders would declare war
on the slaves. Killing them was not
considered homicide. In the late stages
of the Roman Republic, there were an
estimated 2 to three million slaves,
including roughly a third of the
population of Rome. Roman slaves were
chatt, the full property of their
owners. Some worked in agricultural
chain gangs. The punishment for runaways
was often crucifixion. After a slave
rebellion in 71 BC, the Roman general
Marcus Lascinius Cassus crucified 6,000
slaves on the road from Capua to Rome. a
dead slave mounted to a cross every 100
ft or so. The word slavery itself
provides some insight into just how
ubiquitous slavery has been throughout
history. Slave comes directly from the
ethnic term Slav because the people who
lived in central and eastern Europe,
Slavic peoples were so frequently
captured and sold into slavery from the
8th to 11th centuries. Slavery was
widespread outside of Europe too. Of
course, according to the anthropologist
Pierre [music]
Vanenberg, war captives and slaves were
systematically humiliated and often
tortured to death in some North American
Indian societies. Among some South
American groups of the Amazon
rainforest, slaves were wellfed, but
only in preparation for a cannibalistic
feast preceded by a mock battle in which
the slave would be clubbed to death.
Often, slavery was a simple function of
power dynamics. As countries rose and
fell, they'd shift from enslavers to the
enslaved. Consider the case of the
Irish. In the early fifth century, as
the power of Rome declined, Irish
marauders frequently raided the British
coast for loot and slaves. Thousands of
men, women, and children were taken. In
one raid on the village of Bonav Ternier
near modern-day Wales, Irish raiders
kidnapped a 16-year-old boy named Sakat.
Sakat spent six years as a slave at a
sheep farm in Northern Ireland. He later
escaped, returned home, became a priest,
and came back to the land of his
captivity as a missionary. And we know
him today as St. Patrick, patron saint
of Ireland. By 795 AD, the tides had
turned and now Vikings were enslaving
the Irish along with many other northern
Europeans. Viking slaves were seen as
cattle or as advanced domestic animals
who typically lived in the darkest end
of the long house with the other
domestic animals. After Oliver Cromwell
conquered Ireland in the mid- 17th
century, the situation reversed and the
Irish were at the mercy of their former
captives. The new English regime forced
the relocation of roughly 80,000 Irish
men, women, and children to sugar
colonies in the Caribbean where they
were held in bondage and forced to work
in the fields. Not easy to do with an
Irish complexion. By the way,
most of us have no idea what
phytonutrients actually are, but
thankfully our sponsor, Balance of
Nature, understands the importance of
them. Phytonutrients are naturally
occurring plant nutrients in whole foods
that actually give fruits and vegetables
their color, taste, and smell. If you're
eating something with vibrant color and
real flavor, it's a pretty good sign
you're getting genuine phytonutrients.
Now, what Balance Nature does is take
all that produce and run it through a
specialized vacuum cold process that
keeps everything stable, then powders it
down. Their whole health system is
essentially a value bundle that combines
their fruits, veggies, and their uh
fiber and spice supplements. So, you're
getting 47 different ingredients,
fruits, vegetables, spices, and fibers
along with all those naturally occurring
phytonutrients every single day. I
personally love the whole health system
because of its convenience when I'm
traveling for work or trying to keep up
with the kids. gives me a simple, no
mess and no stress way to make sure I'm
getting all the essential nutrients in
my diet. So whether you've been on the
fence for a long time or it's the first
time you're hearing about them, I
recommend that you go to balanced
nature.com and order the whole health
system uh supplement as a preferred
customer today. It's [snorts] a
statistical reality that every living
white person has ancestors who were
enslaved, but a great deal of white
slavery was not done by fellow
Europeans. This is the town of Baltimore
in County Cork, Ireland. The tranquility
of its rocky shoreline was shattered on
the night of June 20th, 1631.
That evening at precisely 2:00 in the
morning, Islamic pirates led by a
commander named Morat the younger
arrived banging war drums and screaming
in Arabic. They arrived on two large
raiding vessels flying crescent moon
flags, one 300 ton flagship equipped
with 200 men and 24 pieces of ordinance,
including 12 cannons on each side and a
smaller, more maneuverable 100 ton ship
with six iron guns on each side. It came
as a shock to the Irish villagers who
were mostly fishermen. According to a
book called The Stolen Village, quote,
"None of these untraveled fisher folk
would ever have seen anything like the
Turkish warriors with their flashing
scimitars, their swirling, flowing robes
with distinctive cowls, the torch light
glistening on the sweat of bare arms,
which they contemptuously left
unprotected by armor." "Storm them, my
brave ones." Some of the janiseries
would have been yelling, while others
responded with shouts of, "Allah!
Allah!" These pirates were janiseries
and they were raised from a young age to
become fearsome monk-like fighters for
the Ottoman Empire. Their story offers a
good look into the proliferation of
slavery. The forced levy of Christians
to become geniseries is called the
Devshshire system and it involved the
kidnapping of hundreds of thousands of
Christian boys over the 300 years that
it was in place. After they were
kidnapped, they were forcibly converted
to Islam. They were extraordinarily
disciplined and well equipped. They
carried musketss and pistols carried in
a red scarf tied around their waist as
well as their signature double curved
blades. The Janiseries had spent weeks
sailing to Baltimore from Alers 1,200 m
away preparing silently for precisely
this moment. And when that moment
arrived, the Jisseries were prepared.
The villagers were not. Outnumbered 10
to1, the citizens of Baltimore never
stood a chance. Neither did the British
Navy, which was responsible for
patrolling the coast and protecting
villages like Baltimore from attack. The
British knew through good intelligence
gathering in Aliers, that the Janiseries
were planning an attack, but expected it
to happen at a much larger and wealthier
town called Kinsale, 50 mi away. Through
a captured and likely tortured
fishermen, the Janiseries learned that
the British fleet had left Baltimore
unguarded, and they planned to move into
the interior of the country to collect
more Irish slaves. But Irish ingenuity
claimed the day. Resourceful villagers
gathered nearby, collected firearms and
rum, and started making as much noise as
possible. This convinced the pirates
that an English army was marching on
them, and they retreated from Baltimore,
limiting themselves to around 100
slaves. The raid on Baltimore is unique
because of where it happened, but such
raids into Europe were fairly common. In
1627, for example, corsairs took five
ships in a raid on remote Hey Island in
Iceland. With total ferocity, they
killed and maimed. They raped the women
and girls, dismembered infants,
desecrated churches, and slaughtered a
priest at prayer. They burned and looted
everything in sight, and quote, settled
down to a long unhurried orgy of rape,
mutilation, and murder, which seems to
have been motivated by nothing more than
sadistic sport. One account tells of the
Corsaires cutting people in half and
callously snapping the necks of infants.
Anyone unable to keep up with their pace
was cut down and in their madness for
blood, these villains then chopped and
hacked the bodies into small pieces with
the greatest enjoyment and lust for
blood, wrote one eyewitness. In that
particular raid on Iceland, the
Corsaires kidnapped half the island's
population. They murdered one in 12
villagers, including several priests.
All in all, they returned alers with
roughly 400 slaves taken from the coast
of Iceland. And along the way, they
would seize church bells and attach them
to the mass of their ships as trophies.
They destroyed crucifixes and mocked
Christians by destroying the Eucharist
at every opportunity. According to the
book, The Forgotten Slave Trade,
historian Simon Webb described this
shocking contemporaneous account. Quote,
"They began to set fire to the houses.
There was a woman there, could not walk,
whom they had captured easily. her. They
threw on the fire along with her
two-year-old baby. When she and the poor
child screamed and called to God for
help, the wicked Turks bellowed with
laughter. They struck both child and
mother with the sharp points of their
spears, forcing them into the fire. They
even stabbed fiercely at the poor
burning bodies. In just 7 days, the
historian Des Ekin writes, "The typical
medium-sized Corsair ship usually seized
five vessels, enslaved nearly 100
Englishmen, and stole roughly 60,000
pounds. Victims who weren't killed in
many cases became galley slaves. Since
the Roman era, galley slaves were
considered the most effective way to
keep the galleys moving since they
required coordinated rowing. If anyone
took a break, they'd make the ship much
less efficient. Webb notes that after a
naval battle in 1571 between the Ottoman
Empire and the Holy League, which
included Spain and Venice, became
evident just how many Christians had
been forced to row boats for the
Ottomans, and what horrific conditions
these Galley slaves had to endure.
Following the battle, the Holy League
discovered that more than 12,000
European Christians have been forced to
row the GS for the Ottomans. They were
shackled 24 hours a day. They were not
afforded the opportunity to lie down to
sleep. Not that there was any room to do
so. In any event, Webb writes that
quote, "A typical galley might have 25
ores on each side and perhaps three to
five rowers for each ore. The slaves
were shackled in place and were
therefore physically unable to move from
their designated positions." It was said
in the 16th century that a galley crewed
by slaves could be smelled from as far
away as a mile. This was unlikely to be
an exaggeration. Imagine if you will
hundreds of men confined in a narrow
space and compelled by nature to open
their bladders and bowels where they
were seated day in and day out for years
at a time. There was no provision for
washing. The only prospect of escape for
the Ottoman galley slaves was if ships
of a Christian nation defeated the
Ottomans. A more dreadful fate is
difficult to imagine. But not all slaves
were forced to row the galleys. After
returning to Algeria, some slaves, men,
women, and children were put up for the
auction. Children as young as 12 years
old were sold as concubines. In a normal
auction, children younger than seven
could sell for over £100, roughly double
the asking price for an attractive
woman. Between 1500 and 1800 AD, the
Ottomans and their North African
corsairs, also called Barbarie pirates
likely enslaved roughly a million and a
half people from Christian Europe.
Unlike the transatlantic slave trade,
which was driven by pure profit, the
Barbar raids on Europe were motivated by
blood lust and hatred. One historian
described it as revenge, almost a jihad,
for the expulsion of Muslims from Spain
in 1492, for the centuries of crusading
violence that had preceded them and for
the ongoing religious struggle between
Christians and Muslims. In the first
half of the 17th century, Barbar slavers
were sailing through the English Channel
and into the Tempame's estuary,
plundering local shipping and coastal
towns, such that, as the minutes of
Parliament put it, the fishermen are
afraid to put to sea and were forced to
keep continual watch on all our coasts.
By 1640, at least 3,000 British
nationals were enslaved in Alers alone.
In just the 7-year stretch from6009 to
1616, 466
English ships were quote boarded and the
crews taken to North Africa as slaves.
In April 1625, three ships from Cornwall
and one sailing from Dartmouth in Devon
were captured by Corsairs and the crews
taken. In August 1625, a raiding party
landed at Mounts Bay in Cornwall. The
villagers saw the ships at anchor and
fled for safety to a local church. But
this was not enough to save them. The
slavers dragged 60 people out of the
church, loaded them onto their rowing
boats, and took them on board the
waiting ships. They all ended up in the
slave markets of North Africa. The 12th
of that month, the mayor of Plymouth
wrote to the Privy Council in London. He
pleaded for assistance from the Navy
because in 10 days, 27 ships have been
taken and all of the men on board, over
200 of them, have been made slaves. As
bad as it was to be in British waters,
it was worse in southern Europe. Muslim
raids on the northern shore of the
Mediterranean were almost annual events
of terror and pillage. In 1544 in the
Bay of Naples, Algerians took 6,000
captives. 6,000 more Italians were taken
during the sack of Vieste in Calabria.
In 1566, they took 4,000 slaves in
Granada, Spain in a single raid. They
described it as reigning Christians in
Alers. The list goes on. In 1617, 1,200
men in Madira in 1636. Another 700 in
Calabria, Italy. Then a thousand more in
1639, and 4,000 more in 1644. In 1683,
the French military attempted to free
some of the slaves being held in Alger.
The Algerians didn't take kindly to it.
Quote, "Infuriated at their helplessness
and the face of such an attack, the
Algerians decided to vent their anger
upon those Frenchmen who were at their
mercy, including Jean Lavves, Alers had
at the time the most powerful cannon in
the whole of the Mediterranean. It
weighed 12 tons. The 23-t long gun had a
range of 3 mi. The unfortunate French
console was pushed partly into the
barrel. The cannon then being discharged
with a load of shrapnel, blowing him to
pieces. The Algerians found 22 other
Frenchmen and tied them to the muzzles
of other guns and killed them the same
way. When it comes to protecting
yourself and your family, it's better to
be prepared. That's why I'm a member of
Ammo Squared. Ammo Squared lets you
build an ammo reserve of your calibers
steadily month by month without drama or
excuses. Your options are endless. They
have 75 caliber variations from over 85
ammunition manufacturers. There's also
no need to have extra storage space
laying around your house. They handle
all the storage for you so you can get
what you need when you need. I found it
super convenient and sensible. And it's
great to know my selected supply is
ready to be delivered at any time. Start
getting prepared now and think ahead
with Amos Squared. Go to amosquared.com
today and become a member like me.
Now, for the most part, these slaves,
unless they were ransomed or executed
inside a cannon, spent the rest of their
lives in North Africa and the Ottoman
Empire, which incidentally is one of
those colonial empires that no one on
the left seems to mind, assuming they're
even aware of it. One of the most
shocking slave trades did not involve
Europeans at all. It involved an Arabun
slave trade operation in East Africa,
roughly around the same time as the
Middle Passage was bringing slaves from
places like the home to Brazil. But
unlike slaves arriving in the new world,
Arabs frequently castrated male slaves
to prevent them from breeding. The
castration process was in some cases so
brutal that 80 to 90% died during the
operation. It wasn't just castration
leading to mass deaths. Conditions were
so brutal that three out of four died
before even getting to market. The East
African slave trade included legendary
traders like the black ivory merchant
Hamemed bin Muhammad al- Murgebby, also
known as Tippu Tip, who organized the
removal of between 50,000 to 100,000
slaves from the Congo to move ivory to
markets on the coast. Al Mergeby earned
his nickname Tippu Tip from the sounds
his men's guns made during their raiding
parties into the Congo. When he finally
brought his slaves to the African coast
with their ivory, they were then
auctioned off to the highest bidder. So
many slaves moved through East Africa
that Zanzibar became the biggest slave
market in the world. By some estimates,
as many as 17 million East Africans were
sold into slavery over,300 years,
dwarfing the transatlantic slave trade.
Many of them worked spice fields and
plantations in East Africa. And the
practice wasn't abolished until 1909,
once again because of colonizers, this
time from Britain. Now, the reality is
that the East African slave trade, which
exceeded the West African slave trade in
its duration, barbarity, and quantity of
slaves, has received relatively little
attention from academics and
journalists. That's because it's not a
useful tool for a demoralization
campaign against white Americans. White
Americans, by the way, whose ancestors
were enslaved as well.
On the morning of June 14th, 1786,
Captain James Moore's family woke up on
what seemed to be a normal day in
Southwest Virginia. But as they left the
family's cabin to tend to their farm
animals, the fearful war whoop was
heard, and a raiding party of Ohio
Valley Shauny Indians rode down a
rgeline and attacked them. Captain Moore
was shot seven times before being
tomahawkked and scalped. The Indians
then murdered three of his children,
leaving only his family members who were
locked inside the cabin. Much like the
Barbarie pirates, the Indians broke into
the house, shot the dogs, plundered and
burned the home, killed the livestock,
and took Moore's wife and surviving
children captive. The raiding party
stole horses and embarked on a journey
to Detroit, which was then an open air
market for humans captured by Indians.
To give you a sense of the savagery of
the Indians, when one of the surviving
sons, John, fell behind on the journey,
Indians split his head open with a
tomahawk and then told Jon's mother what
happened with her son's bloody scalp
hanging in his waistband. They reached
Detroit in December where in a drunken
frolic, one of the surviving daughters,
Mary Moore, was sold into slavery for a
few gallons of rum to a man named
Stagwell, who had been an active Tory
during the war and had removed to Canada
after it closed for fear of losing his
life if he remained in the United
States. 3 years later, she was rescued
by her brother and returned to United
States. Stories like Mary Moore's were
common in the early frontier period in
America, and often the stories became
nationwide bestsellers. The vast
majority of white slaves in the United
States were owned by fellow whites.
Somewhere between 60 and 70% of white
immigrants to the American colonies
arrived in bondage, often involuntarily.
An estimated 350,000
arrived between 1620 and 1776 in numbers
that likely far exceeded the number of
black slaves who arrived in the 1600s.
Mortality rates on the journey to the
colonies often exceeded 20%. Many of
them were legally classified as
indentured servants under British law.
Indentured servitude was in theory a
contract entered between a poor person
and a sponsor in which the sponsor pays
for the poor person's transit across the
Atlantic in exchange for a set period of
bondage. That however is the textbook
definition. Reality was much harsher. In
the early colonial period, there were
not substantial differences between
indentured servants and black slaves.
Many were subjected to conditions of
such brutality, duration, and
heritability that historians
increasingly regard slave as the more
accurate term. There's no question that
indentured servitude was slavery. Some
indenture contracts literally use the
term slave, and ads issued for runaway
servants asked for them to be returned
to their masters. Some of them were held
in bondage for life. Many of them were
sent here against their will. At the
outbreak of the revolution in 1776, more
than 50,000 convicts were sent to the
colonies as slave laborers. There were
all sorts of sources of white slavery.
They were the convicts, the urban poor,
political prisoners, thieves,
prostitutes, vagrants, prisoners of war,
anyone designated undesirable by the
British government. In the winter of
1650, 150 ragged Scottish prisoners of
war arrived at Massachusetts Bay Colony
where they were sold as indentured
laborers for 20 to 30 pounds each. And
colonial America, white and black slaves
often bonded. According to NPR, which
admits America's first slaves were
white. According to some uh
African-American historians, they got a
there was no sign or little sign of uh
racial tension between the English
servants, which we reckon were slaves,
and the African servants are also called
servants. They were treated in much the
same way for many decades. They
complained together, they ran away
together, they rebelled together.
>> George Washington himself had white
slaves. uh the beginning of your war of
independence, the Revolutionary War,
there were ads in the Virginia Gazette
[music] for runaways. And I think there
were that week there were something like
11 for white runaways and three for
black runaways. And two of the 11 white
runaways were being advertised by George
Washington.
>> In early Virginia and Maryland,
indentured servants, mostly English,
Irish, and Scottish, did the same jobs
that enslaved Africans would do in the
19th century, mostly tobacco farming.
Conditions were so bad that 40 to 50%
died before completing their terms. A
1671 report from Virginia Governor
William Berkeley noted that the number
of white slaves arriving vastly
outnumbered black. Quote, "We suppose
there come in of servants about 1,500,
of which most are English, a few Scotch,
a few Irish, and not above two or three
ships of Negroes in seven years." He
then went on to note that in the early
years of the colony, 80% of servants did
not survive the first year. But it
wasn't just the slaves that were
multi-racial. It was the slave holders,
too. At slavery's peak in 1860,
thousands of slaves were owned by
Chakdas, Cherokees, Creeks, and Chasaw
Indians. As Alan Taylor writes in the
book American Colonies, the Uriccoy were
particularly brutal [music] in this
regard. In colonial America, the Irakcoy
would often subject captives. the ones
they did not enslave to ritualistic
slaughter and cannibalism in which
captives would be tied to the stake,
stabbed, then prodded with hot pokers.
Quote, "After the victim died, the women
butchered his remains, cast them into
cooking kettles, and serve the stew to
the entire village so that all could be
bound together in absorbing [music] the
captives power." At the outbreak of the
Civil War, one of South Carolina's
wealthiest citizens was a planter and
slaveholder named William Ellison.
Census records show that at the outset
of the Civil War, he owned 63 slaves,
making him one of the biggest slave
owners in the region. During the Civil
War, he and his sons made substantial
donations to the Confederate government.
But what makes Allison remarkable is
that he was a black man. In fact, he was
a freed slave whose former master had
given him the business skills he [music]
needed to become a successful cotton gin
manufacturer. He was such a prominent
member of South Carolina society that
the Charleston Mercury [music] newspaper
noted that he was a large slaveholder
and is much respected throughout the
district for his integrity and general
good character. When the American
journalist and social critic Frederick
Law Olmstead visited Mississippi in the
early 1860s, he described meeting a
black man who told him there were quote
many free negroes all about this region.
Some were very rich. He pointed out to
me three plantations within 20 m owned
by colored men. They bought black folks,
he said, and had servants of their own.
They were very bad masters, very hard
and cruel. If he had got to be sold, he
would like best to have an American
master by him. The French black creole
masters were very severe, and they
whipped their nwords [music] most to
death. They whipped the flesh off them.
In total, an estimated 3,000 blacks
owned roughly 20,000 slaves in 1860. And
in some cases, black slave holders
purchase relatives and spouses
philanthropically, rescuing them from
other slaveholders. But according to the
black historian [music] Carter Godwin
Woodson, they often simply bought and
sold slaves like white traders. He even
described one case in which, quote, "A
negro shoemaker in Charleston, South
Carolina, purchased his wife for $700,
but on finding her hard to please, he
sold her a few months thereafter for
$750."
The 1860 census offers some context
that's uh left out of the history
textbooks in this country. That year
there were 3,953,760
slaves and 487,970
total free colored population in the
slave states in 1860. The reality is
that a very small percentage of freed
blacks and American Indians own slaves.
But the same is true for white
Americans. In the 1860 census, at the
very height of slavery, there were
393,975
slave owners in [music] the US, out of a
total population of over 31 million.
That translates to about 1.2% of the
population. The vast majority of
American whites never owned any slaves.
That's a critical point when in the
context of modern calls for reparations.
As a rule, black slaves in the American
South had a life expectancy of 40 years
and an annual mortality rate of 3 to 5%.
Their odds of getting married, having
children, attaining freedom were
dramatically higher than slaves in the
Caribbean, Brazil, East Africa, or god
forbid to homie. Slaves in the Caribbean
lived in barracks. In the south, they
had cabins. There's no doubt that being
a slave was a bad life, but if you were
to be enslaved, it was better to be
enslaved in the United States. The
clearest metric on this is that the US
slaves population kept growing after
slave imports were banned in 1808.
Unlike other parts of the Americas where
deaths exceeded births, the US ended up
with nearly 4 million slaves in 1860
despite only 400,000 arrivals. Now, one
reason for the better conditions could
be incentives. With the import ban,
slave owners best source of slaves was
high birth rates. Buying more was really
expensive. Typical price for an
able-bodied male field hand in New
Orleans in 1860 was about $2,000. And if
you track inflation based on the price
of gold, that'd be over $100,000 today.
For this reason, there are
welldocumented cases of slaveholders
preferring to use less valuable lowerass
whites for dangerous tasks. Our sponsor,
Grand Canyon University, is an
affordable private Christian university
based in beautiful Phoenix, Arizona, one
of the largest universities in the
country. Widely praised for its culture
of community and impact, GCU is uh 369
academic programs with over 300 of those
available online. At GCU, you'll join a
nationwide community of learners who are
redefining online education through
their 100% online MBA program. Learn
about ethical entrepreneurship, how to
scale your business, and so much more.
In addition to federal grants and aid,
GCU's online students received nearly
$161 million in institutional
scholarships in 2024, making it one of
the most affordable private Christian
education options out there. So take the
chance and find your purpose at Grand
Cancy University. Visit gcu.edu/myoffer
to see the scholarships that you may
qualify for. In 1800, there was not a
single country on earth that had
abolished slavery by law. Not one. By
1900, Britain, France, the United
States, Denmark, the Netherlands, Spain,
Portugal had all outlawed it. Every
single abolition took place in societies
under European control or heavy European
pressure. In a perfect Orwellian twist
of irony, it turns out white men are the
heroes of the slavery story. It was the
Royal Navy's West Africa squadron that
freed hundreds of thousands of African
slaves, all done at the expense of the
British taxpayer. It was the nearly
400,000 Union soldiers who died in the
American Civil War and the entirely
white Congress and white legislators
that passed the 13th Amendment ending
slavery. If the legacy of slavery is a
permanent unpayable debt that justifies
racial redistribution in perpetuity,
then literally every ethnic group on the
planet owes every other one. The
descendants of the Kingdom of Deomi,
which sold millions of their fellow
Africans, would owe reparations to the
descendants of their victims. The Arab
world would owe West Africa and Europe.
The Ottomans would owe the Balkans, the
Irish would owe the English, and the
English would owe the Irish. The list is
endless because slavery is the norm, not
America's unique shame. But only one
civilization ever decided the guilt
outweighed the profit and bled itself
dry to end it. That's the real story.
They don't teach. What do Snow White,
Cinderella, and Smallox blankets have in
common? They're all fairy tales. For
decades, you've been told that you live
on stolen land.
>> We are right now on stolen land.
>> That the Indians were peaceful.
>> Native Americans, we massacred [music]
them.
>> Your ancestors committed genocide.
And guess what? None of it is true. The
Native Americans were some of the most
savage fighters ever known to man.
raiding, [music] scalping, torturing,
even eating enemies. It was better to
lose a battle to the US Army [music]
than to get wiped out by a rival tribe.
And why did the story completely change
in the 1960s? It turns out there's a lot
more to the American Indians than
Hollywood directors and school teachers
want you to know. This month, we blow up
the biggest myths [music] about the
American Indians and reclaim the real
history that was stolen from us. This is
[music] the real history of the American
Indian.
>> [music]